<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian Commonvvealth: or, The civil policy of the rising kingdom of Jesus Christ. Written before the interruption of the government, by Mr. John Eliot, teacher of the Church of Christ at Roxbury in New-England. And now published (after his consent given) by a server of the season.</title>
            <author>Eliot, John, 1604-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1001_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866873</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E1001[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian Commonvvealth: or, The civil policy of the rising kingdom of Jesus Christ. Written before the interruption of the government, by Mr. John Eliot, teacher of the Church of Christ at Roxbury in New-England. And now published (after his consent given) by a server of the season.</title>
                  <author>Eliot, John, 1604-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Livewell Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 26 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Kingdom --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Chriſtian COMMONVVEALTH: OR, The Civil Policy Of The Riſing Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Written Before the Interruption of the Government, by Mr. <hi>John Eliot,</hi> Teacher of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Roxbury</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Now Publiſhed (after his conſent given) by a Server of the Seaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi>: Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119161:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119161:2"/>
            <head>To the Choſen, and Holy, and Faithful, who manage the Wars of the Lord, againſt Antichriſt, in great <hi>Britain;</hi> and to all the Saints, faithful Brethren, and Chriſtian people, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England:</hi> Grace and Mercy, with Peace and Truth be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, through Jeſus Chriſt our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord and King.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Ever Honoured, and Beloved in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He late great Changes, which have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len out in great <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> haue ſo amazed the moſt of men; and the black, and confuſed Clouds, which have over-ſpread the whole Land, have ſo darkened the way of thoſe wheels of Providence by which Chriſt is coming to ſet up his Kingdom, that they whoſe eyes the Lord hath begun to open, to ſee Chriſt coming, in power and in great glory, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:119161:3"/>
to his Promiſe, do alſo ſee the other part of his word verified, namely, that the coming of Christ is in the Clouds of darkneſs; by means whereof it is long ere all men can ſee him, or be perſwaded that it is he, who is now coming; though afterwards, they ſhall ſee that even thoſe Clouds were needful, a while to obſcure the bright appearance of his deſign.</p>
            <p>Lately reading a Book called a <hi>Plea for Non-ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers,</hi> or the grounds and reaſons of many Ministers of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire, &amp;c.</hi> though I had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heard of the ſad differences, diſtances of ſpirit, and diſſatisfactions among the people of the Lord: yet then my heart bled to ſee ſuch precious holy men, pleading (as they believe) for God, with a pure and ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and yet in ſo doing strongly to ſpeak againſt the glorious work of the Lord Jeſus, in caſting down Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and ſetting up his own Kingdom foretold in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and now fulfilling, as alſo ſtrongly and ſharply ſpeaking againſt thoſe whom the Lord hath pleaſed to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, and improve as his Inſtruments in accompliſhing thereof.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, thoſe writings which that Book An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, have ſo miſſed the Principles on which the Cauſe ſtandeth, whereby the Conſciences of others ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, who oppoſe; as that the Anſwerers have clearly the upper ground of them in many things: and therefore ſtand firme in that which they ſuppoſe to be a right Cauſe, and weaken thoſe who have indeed a right Cauſe in hand, inſomuch as that hereby the difference is exceedingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and ſharpened.</p>
            <p>Now though I am the moſt unmeet of all men, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to interpoſe and ſpeak unto ſuch learned, grave,
<pb facs="tcp:119161:3"/>
holy, and eminent perſons, every way beyond me in all accompliſhments for the Lords work, and in a Cauſe ſo much above me; yet was I preſſed in my ſpirit, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering whoſe Cauſe I plead, to take the boldneſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound that unto them, which I believe to be the true ſtate of the Cauſe, and which (by the bleſſing of God) may reach to their ſatisfaction; when they ſee that they, into whoſe hands the Lord (to the wonderment of men) hath been pleaſed to put power, do follow the Lord, and accompliſh his Word, aim at the fulfilling of his ends and deſign, denying themſelves, that they may advance Chriſt Jeſus in the Throne, and let him reign over them. The pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the expectation, and faith of the Saints, in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies and Promiſes of holy Scripture, are daily ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ears of the Lord, for the downfall of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and with him all humane Powers, Polities, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and Governments; and in the room thereof, we wait for the coming of the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus, who by his Divine Wiſdom, Power, Government and Laws, given us (although hitherto ſealed up in a great meaſure) in the holy Scriptures, will reign over all the Nations of the earth in his due time: I mean, the Lord Jeſus will bring down all people, to be ruled by the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, Laws, and Directions of the Word of God; not only in Church-Government and Adminiſtrations, but alſo in the Government and Administration of all affairs in the Commonwealth. And then Chriſt reigneth, when all things among men, are done by the direction of the word of his mouth: his Kingdom is then come amongst us, when his will is done on earth, as it is done in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; where no Humane or Angelical Policy or Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doth guide any thing, but all is done by Divine
<pb facs="tcp:119161:4"/>
direction <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 20. Angels do his commandment, hearkening to the voice of his word.</note>; and ſo it ſhall be on earth, when, and where Chriſt reigneth.</p>
            <p>It is Propheſied, Dan. <hi>2. 34, 35,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 34, 35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>till that a ſtone was cut out, without hands, which ſmote the image upon his feet that were of iron and clay, and brake them to pieces. 35. Then was the iton, the clay, the braſs, the ſilver, and the gold, broken to pieces together, and became like the chaff of the ſummer threſhing-floors; and the wind carried them away, that no place was found for them: and the ſtone that ſmote the image, became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth,</hi> &amp;c. Which Prophecie doth clearly foreſhew the forenamed points: for there is an epitomy of all the Monarchies, Governments, and Polities of men, who have had their Humane Glory in this world: the laſt, and ſtrongeſt of all which Dominions is the Roman; ſo mixed and interwoven in many States, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bining of that dirty Roman Religion, with civil Powers, as that when that ſtone Chriſt, by his faithful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall overthrow, and beat in pieces that Religion, they muſt and ſhall, according as it is written, beat down withall the strongeſt Iron ſinews of oivil States, which are propugnators, and ſupporters thereof, whether pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed or ſecretly.</p>
            <p>Yea, moreover, when Chriſt that ſtone, ſhall by his choſen Inſtruments, ſmite in pieces all the Romiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and civil States, which are complicated with it, and ſupporters of it, (who though they greatly care not
<pb facs="tcp:119161:4"/>
for it <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 43. They ſhall not cleave one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even as iron is not mixt with clay.</note>, yet for their own ends they are ſupporters of it) then, down cometh the whole Image from top to bottom; all Dominions and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of man, by Humane Policy, formes of Government and Laws in all places what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, in Gods order and time; who by their fall ſhall be ſo paſhed in pieces, that though they were before, a terrour to men, yet now they ſhall be light and contemptible things, of no more account with men then duſt or chaff: becauſe Divine institutions, both of Government and Laws, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the room of Humane, they will be quite darkened, even as the Stars are by the riſing-Sun: for in the room of them ſhall ariſe the Government of the Lord Jeſus, who by the Word of his Mouth, written in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, ſhall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der all affairs among men; And great ſhall be his Dominion: for the Stone Christ ſhall grow to be a mountain filling the whole earth: all men ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be ruled by the Word, in civil, as well as Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affairs.</p>
            <p>Now it ſeemeth to me that the Lord Chriſt is now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing theſe things in great <hi>Britain.</hi> The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> gave the firſt blow at the dirty toes, and feet of this Image; with whom the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful brethren in <hi>England,</hi> preſently concurred. But the Iron of the Civil State, ſtuck ſo faſt to the miry clay, that according to the Word of Chriſt, they are (beyond all the thoughts of men) both fallen together; they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, they are fallen, they are both fallen together: Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord, for his faithful Word, and goodneſs; for his mercy endurteh for ever! and all his faithful Word ſhall be accompliſhed. Amen, Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:5"/>
There be many other Prophecies of holy Scriptures touching theſe things (as the Saints well know) the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication whereof to what is now done in <hi>England,</hi> I will not undertake, it being a worke rather for a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe then a Preface. Yea, ſome Prophecies, (as I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend) do more particularly deſcribe what is now done; but I ſhall not mention them, hoping that others will do it, according as the Lord ſhall pleaſe to open that door.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things being ſo, it doth deeply concern thoſe holy and faithful ones of the Lord, who have been Instruments in his hand, to accompliſh theſe great and glorious works, whether by Councils or Wars, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to be wiſe, and diſcerning of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do, in this great work of bringing about the Kingdom to <hi>David,</hi> to lay the Government upon his ſhoulders: that after all theſe clouds and ſtorms, the peaceable Kingdom of Chriſt may riſe up, and the Lord may reign in <hi>England.</hi> Much is ſpoken of the rightful Heir of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the unjuſtice of caſting out the right Heir: but Chriſt is the only right Heir of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2. 8. The uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</note>, and of all other Nations alſo <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 15. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this world are become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt; and he ſhall reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; and he is now come to take poſſeſſion of his Kingdom, making <hi>England</hi> first in that bleſſed work of ſetting up the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus: and in order thereunto, he hath caſt down not only the miry Religion, and Government of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but alſo the former form of civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which did ſtick ſo faſt unto it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til by an unavoidable neceſſity, it fell with it; which while it ſtood, and as it ſtood, was too
<pb facs="tcp:119161:5"/>
high to ſtoop to the Lord Jeſus, to be ruled by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Now therefore by theſe preparations made by the naked Arm of the Lord Jeſus, to ſet up his Kingdom in <hi>England,</hi> he calleth upon thoſe Worthies into whoſe hands he hath betruſted the managing of this great work, now to advance Chriſt, not man; not themſelves, but Chriſt; which doing, taketh off thoſe heavy imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of inveſting themſelves with Authority, of taking the Inheritance to themſelves—God forbid, God forbid, that it ſhould enter into our hearts, to think ſo unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo unchriſtianly, ſo diſhonourably of ſuch renowned ſervants of the Lord, who have ſo graciouſly, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ever given unto the Lord, all the glory of all their Victories, that now at laſt they ſhould rob him of his Crown, Dominion, and Government; which to ſet up in <hi>England,</hi> hath been the mark and Scope of all theſe late great works of God; and if it be not yet done, ſurely it is either becauſe the Lord hath not yet fully revealed to them, what his will is they ſhould do in the midst of theſe confuſions, or becauſe the unquietneſs of the times per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits them not to go about it.</p>
            <p>That which the Lord now calleth <hi>England</hi> to attend, is not to ſearch humane Polities and Platformes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, contrived by the wiſdom of man; but as the Lord hath carried on their works for them, ſo they ought to go unto the Lord, and enquire at the Word of his mouth, what Platforme of Government he hath therein commanded and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcribed; and humble themſelves to embrace that as the beſt, how mean ſoever it may ſeem to Humane Wiſdom. Faith can ſee beauty, power and glory in any Divine inſtitution, when Humane Wiſdom may think it weak and contemptible.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:6"/>
There is undoubtedly a forme of Civil Government in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by God himſelf in the holy Scriptures; whereby any Nation may enjoy all the ends and effects of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the beſt manner, were they but perſwaded to make trial of it. We ſhould derogate from the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and perfection of the Scriptures, if we ſhould deny it. The Scripture is able throughly to furniſh the man of God (whether Magistrate in the Commonwealth, or Elder in the Church, or any other) unto every good work.</p>
            <p>And when a Christian people are to chooſe their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſhould they take their Patern from the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5. Make us a King to judge us like all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>, we know what an offence that would be to Chriſt, who intends to Rule them himſelf, by his own Divine Patern and Direction. Chriſt is now about to ruine the Roman-Image; Wiſdom therefore it is, to look above all ſuch Paterns to find out a Divine Platforme, taught by God himſelf, which he will delight to bleſs unto ſuch men as ſhall ſubmit unto it.</p>
            <p>And if there be a Divine inſtitution of civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that may ſuit the State of <hi>England,</hi> I doubt not but all the godly in the Land would chuſe that way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment before any other in the World: for every Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution hath a Divine bleſſing in it. Yea, God himſelf is more eminently preſent, ruling thereby; and the Spirit of God doth breath in and bleſs every inſtitution of the Word, to make it powerful and effectual to attain its end better, and more effectually then any Humane Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and Inſtitution in the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ld can do. The Promiſe alſo of Gods bleſſing and protection is unto all thoſe, who walk in Scripture-ways and Ordinances. Moreover, that uncomfortable difference among the people of God about that great buſineſs of changing the
<pb facs="tcp:119161:6"/>
Government in <hi>England,</hi> would hereby be reconciled, and all things brought unto an holy peace, every one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily yielding that the Lord Jeſus ſhould aſſume the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, to appoint them what Government to ſet up over them: and would moſt readily embrace that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lord himſelf, ſhould reign in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think it needful to inſert this word of Apology for my ſelf; That it pleaſed the Lord of his free mercy to me (in my ſelf being no way fitted for ſuch a work) to put me on, to inſtruct our poor, blind, and dark Indians, in the good knowledge of the Lord: who when (through grace) they taſted of the knowledge of God, of themſelves, of Chriſt and redemption by him; they deſired to leave their wild and ſcattered manner of life, and come under Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Order; which did put me upon ſearch, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the mind of the Lord in that reſpect. And this VOW I did ſolemnly make unto the Lord concerning them; that they being a people without any forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and now to chuſe; I would endeavour with all my might, to bring them under the Government of the Lord only: Namely, that I would inſtruct them to imbrace ſuch Government, both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, as the Lord hath commanded in the holy Scriptures; and to deduce all their Laws from the holy Scriptures, that ſo they may be the Lords people, ruled by him alone in all things. Which accordingly they have begun to do through grace, covenanting with the Lord, in a day of fasting and prayer, to be the Lords people; and to receive that forme of Government, which they had learned to be a Divine institution in the holy Scriptures. This occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion did firſt put me upon this Study, who am no States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor acquainted with matters of that nature; but
<pb facs="tcp:119161:7"/>
only ſpend my time in the Study of the holy Book of God. But having collected by the Lords help out of the holy Scripture this following forme of Government: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the excellent harmony and order thereof, both in the ſeveral Courts, gradually aſcending one above another, and all caſes among the people coming under ſuch a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and orderly way of receiving ſpeedy iſſue; and all Appeals, having ſuch a free and unprejudiced paſſage, in their gradual aſcent, even to the higheſt, and final determination: Theſe and ſuch other things made me think, that it is a moſt deſirable, and peaceable forme of Government, and ſuitable to any Chriſtian people, who reverence the Word of God; yea, the more eminent and Chriſtian they be, the more ſuitable it is for them.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially alſo conſidering, that though the ſingle form of tens, fifties, hundreds, and thouſands, will be but of ſmall capacity in great Commonwealths, and populous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: yet the ſuperiour orders, of Myriades or ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, fifty thouſands, hundred thouſands, and thouſand thouſands, are exceeding comprehenſive, to extend Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to the greatest people; and yet with that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and peaceable order (without any interfering or confuſion) for ſpeedy Juſtice, and determination of all Cauſes, as that it ſeemeth to me to be the moſt excellent Government that ever was in the World. And adding to this, above all conſiderations and commendations, that it is a DIVINE INSTITUTION, ſprung from heavenly wiſdom commanded in Scripture, filled with the Spirit of God, which is able to carry on the Wheels of this Government, with a most irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſucceſsful force and power, to the attainment of all the ends of Government among men moſt effectually.
<pb facs="tcp:119161:7"/>
Yea, it ſeemeth to me, that this is that forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which Chriſt meaneth to rule all the Nations on earth according to the Scriptures. Yea farther, repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-believing Iſrael and <hi>Judah,</hi> I believe, ſhall ſerve and obey Chriſt in this way of Civil Government; and who knoweth but our obedience hereunto, may haſten and farther their coming in?</p>
            <p>I would not exceed bounds of humble modeſty; yet let me make bold to adventure the producing a farther Meditation, touching the Divinity and heavenly excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this Government of the Lord; namely, that the Angels of Heaven are governed by this order of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according as it is applyable to their condition. It is paſt all doubt, that there is an heavenly order, (I do not ſay Judicature, as with us) among the Angels: for as Hell is a place of confuſion, ſo heaven of order; and if God is the God of order in the Church, whereby the place of his feet is beautified; much more is heaven beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, by a moſt heavenly order of the Church there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding. And if <hi>Solomons</hi> Court was in that reſpect of a raviſhing glory, namely, by the order of it, and of his attendants: much more is heaven in an excellent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all the Angels the holy attendants of Gods Throne, attending in comely order. And if the order of <hi>Solomons</hi> Court, was one effect of his great wiſdom, can we think that the infinite wiſdom of God, attended by Angels, Spirits of ſuch wonderful wiſdom, ſhould not be attended in a moſt glorious order, and his attendantss excellently beautified, by walking in an heavenly order? therefore there is an heavenly order among them. And that it is this order of tens, hundreds, thouſands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth appear in ſeveral Scriptures, where we find menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:119161:8"/>
made of them in this order; wherein it is obſervable, that ſo great is the number of them, that they are not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in their ſingle order; but the loweſt that I have obſerved, is Myriades of Angels, <hi>Heb. 12. 22.</hi> and ſo the Saints ſhall find them ordered when they come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 53. Chriſt maketh mention of twelve Legions of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent aſſiſtance, if he thought good; which is all one with Myriades.</note>. They are alſo mentioned by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of the Superior order, <hi>viz.</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of thouſands; and not only ſo, but by a Supreme order, <hi>viz.</hi> Myriades of Myriades, <hi>Rev. 5. 11.</hi> which I call Supreme, being the higheſt I find mentioned in Scripture: but whether that be the higheſt order of Angels, is not revealed that I know of: but thus it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto me, that the Angels are in this order of Government. Likewiſe the Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeem to be in the ſame order; for when Chriſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to judgement, and all the Saints with him, <hi>1 Theſ. 4. 13.</hi> they ſhall come in this order, <hi>Jude, verſ. 14.</hi> With Myriades of his Saints, behold the Lord cometh.</p>
            <p>Now if this be the order of Government in Heaven, what an heaven upon earth ſhall that be, when all the Kingdoms and Nations on the earth ſhall be ſo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? and then ſhall the will of God be done on earth, as it is done in heaven, when he reigneth over men on earth, in the ſame order of Government as he doth in heaven <note n="b" place="margin">It is not no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that when Chriſt fed the people miraculouſly, he ſet them down by hundreds, and by fifties, <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. 40. as if Chriſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that order.</note>.</p>
            <p>Let me be yet farther bold to propound another Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, under the correction of better judgements, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as I do the former, upon that text <hi>Dan. 7. 10.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:8"/>
where is ſet forth the judgement of God executed upon Antichriſt. Many things might be ſhewed out of the context, to prove, that it is not the last judgement, which is there ſpoken of. The means of execution of that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is by the Wars of the Lamb, the Lord Jeſus, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Book of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> and the people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting thoſe Wars, by this text ſeem to be a people ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by this order of Government: which if it be ſo, may it not give ſome light to find out the ten Kings, which ſhall hate the Whore, make her deſolate and naked, eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire?</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, touching the excellency of this forme of Government, and eſpecially the Divinity of it, and now alſo by a wonderful work of God, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being in a capacity to chuſe unto themſelves a new Government, and in ſuch deep perplexity about that great Queſtion, where to ſet their foot in peace; ſome pleading for the unjuſtice of caſting off the Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, others unſatisfied with the preſent, and all expecting what will be the concluſion. And ſeeing no Humane Forme, quiet and ſafe, to ſet down their foot upon, in rest and tranquillity, hereby all hearts are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, ſighing up to heaven for direction what to do, and where to finde reſt and quiet to the Land. By this means, all hearts are prepared to embrace any help or counſel from the Lord; and when they have wearied themſelves with differences, they will gladly all concur together, to ſet open the door, to let in the Lord Jeſus, to give them reſt; who hath been all this while knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the door, by theſe perplexing troubles: that his Government might be on all hands galdly embraced, and himſelf finde a free and peaceable enterance, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:119161:9"/>
his bleſſed and waited-for reign over the Nations of the earth, according as it is Propheſied in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the King of Saints (whoſe Kingdom I deſire to advance, with all my might and heart) I do beſeech thoſe choſen, and holy and faithful Saints, who by Councils at Home, or by Wars in the Field, have fought the Lords Battels againſt Antichriſt, and have carried on the Cauſe of Chriſt hitherunto, That you would now ſet the Crown of <hi>England</hi> upon the head of Chriſt, whoſe only true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance it is, by the gift of his Father <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2. 8. Ask of me, and I will give thee the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</note>: Let him be your JUDGE, Let him be your LAW-GIVER, Let him be your KING! take the patern and form of your Government, from the Word of his Mouth, which will have power over the Conſciences of all the people of the Land, and compoſe all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences about that point, into a ſweet harmony of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection to Chriſt our Lord and King, with one heart and conſent; and will bring about all the people with one heart, and ſhoulder, to promote the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Chriſt, and yours alſo, when they ſee that yours are not for your ſelves, but for the Lord, to accompliſh all the remainder of the great works of the Lord, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Antichriſt be deſtroyed, and the Throne of the Beaſt burnt with fire, and the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus ſet up in many Nations.</p>
            <p>You bleſſed ones of the Lord, who have ſo eminently, beyond the wont of Conquerors, humbled and abaſed yourſelves, as no-bodies in the work, and aſcribed all the praiſe and glory of your Valiant Atchievments, unto
<pb facs="tcp:119161:9"/>
the Lord Jeſus, whom by faith you did always ſee fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for you, and (to your admiration) getting the Victory for you! You that have with an holy boldneſs of faith, made thoſe dreadful appeals (unheard of in other stories) unto the Lord Jeſus, to witneſs to the ſincerity of your Cauſe and Conſcience by his own arm, and in all your ſtraights have never found him to fail you, or farſake you; but ſtill made you Conquerors, not only of your Enemies, but (which is more) of your ſelves alſo, not to arrogate praiſe unto your ſelves; nor to improve your Victories beyond the bounds of Chriſtian patience and love to the conquered; and all for the honour and glory of Chriſt, and his grace; that his Name and Cauſe might find room and acceptance in the hearts of your Enemies, whom you therefore uſed like Christian Brethren, and not like Enemies.</p>
            <p>Shall ſuch holy ones as you, need perſwaſion to ſet that Crown upon the head of Chriſt, which he hath put into your hands to diſpoſe of? where can you make a better choice, then to take the Lord to be your King? and where can you think to find, a better patern of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, then in the Word of God? and where can you think to finde better Laws, then in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures?</p>
            <p>This following Platform of Government, I do no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther urge, then you ſhall finde it to be purely deduced from the holy Scriptures. It is the holy Scriptures of God onely that I do urge, to be your onely <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> by which you ſhould be ruled in all things; which being, Christ is your King and Soveraign Law-giver, and you are his people ruled by him in all things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:10"/>
And you my dear Brethren, the faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, and all Chriſtian Brethren, who do not yet ſee cauſe of ſubmitting, and yielding unto this Change; I do beſeech you to conſider the times, and compare the Prophecies of Scripture, with the preſent providences; and ſee if you finde not all things to come to paſs, according as it is written; and that theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful providences are not without Scripture-authority, and much to be regarded by the people of God. Nor be they the executions of Divine wrath upon either Church or World, by prophane hands, who act their own wills and luſts, though they accompliſh Gods ends; but they be the pouring out of the wrath of God upon Antichriſt, for his deſtruction, and overthrow of his Kingdom, by the hands of holy Saints, according to the command of Chriſt; Christ himſelf riding forth Victoriouſly among them, and performing his great works, written and foretold in the holy Scriptures. May not Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> coming to the Crown by the help of the Saints, be ſeaſonably called to remembrance? or if not, yet now the time is come, to change Governments, and to caſt down all at the foot of Chriſt, that he may Reign, and fill the Earth with the glory of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>No Oaths or Covenants of Gods People are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, but in ſubordination to him, and to the advancement of his Kingdom. If therefore theſe great Changes are carried up to that head, that is the true ſcope, and end of thoſe Vows and Promiſes. It were not lawful to terminate ſuch a Vow or Covenant, as that is, upon any Perſon, Family or Creature; it were Idolatry; nor was it ſo; nor is it now broken,
<pb facs="tcp:119161:10"/>
by breaking all Creatures in pieces, that ſtood in the way of obtaining the true end thereof, namely, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Lord Jeſus, and his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore help forward this work, which Chriſt hath put into the hands of thoſe whom he hath made eminent, in accompliſhing the works of his glorious coming, to ſet up his Dominion on earth. Be not behind in bringing Chriſt to the Throne in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land!</hi> You, you, the holy Watchmen of the Lord, have given God no rest by your unceſſant Prayers, for the bringing about what is now done; follow on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to follow the Lord, and, as Antichriſt falleth, with whatever elſe ſtood in the way of Chriſt: ſo now let Chriſt come in, and help ye for ward the ſetting up of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I am bold to preſent this Scripture-Platform of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to publique view, (if advice ſo carry it) at this ſeaſon; becauſe I do believe it to be a Divine Inſtitution of a Civil Government; and ſeemeth to me to be ſuch, as will well ſuit the preſent condition of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any other religious people in the World, who fear the command of God, and tremble at his Word: and being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in my heart, that it is the minde of the Lord, that Nations ſhould be governed by Scripture-Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, the time being come that the Lord is about to ſhake all the Earth, and throw down that great Idol of Humane Wiſdome in Governments, and ſet up Scripture-Government in the room thereof. It may pleaſe God to give acceptance unto this poor beginning, and move the hearts of ſuch as are wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:119161:11"/>
to proſecute this deſign of Christ, and more accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſearch the Scriptures, to finde out the perfect will of God in this point, which yet is but in its birth, and dawning; many things being yet dim, and dark: in the morning twilight, we cannot ſee far before us, nor round about us; but the Riſing-Sun, will through grace, bring greater light with him.</p>
            <p>As for ſuch wholſome, juſt, and wiſe Laws, as any Nation hath already made, the Wiſdome of the Lord will teach his People to refer them to their Scripture-principles, demonſtrating the truth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity thereof, by the Word of God, whereby they will appear to be the deducts from the Word of God; and hence they that are governed by them, are gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Lord; they that break them ſin againſt the Lord, by breaking his Commandment and Law.</p>
            <p>It were a Work worthy the labours of the beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and the beſt of Men, to demonſtrate the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the wholſome and wiſe Laws of <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND</hi> by the Word of God; the effects of which Work would be of admirable conſequence to ſanctifie the whole Land, to make the Rulers more expreſly to govern for the Lord, and the People to obey the Lord, in obeying their Governours; and ſo the Lord himſelf ſhould Reign over them.</p>
            <p>My continual Prayer in this behalf, at the Throne of Grace is, that the Lord would ſo far ſcatter thoſe black Clouds, which do darken the mindes of God's
<pb facs="tcp:119161:11"/>
People in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> that they may ſee ſome Beams of the brightneſs of CHRIST his coming to Reign; and that the Lord would pleaſe to bow their divided hearts, to meet with one conſent and accord, to make CHRIST their LAW-GIVER, and JUDGE, and KING, in whom alone they ſhall finde ſettlement and aſſured peace.</p>
            <trailer>Amen, Amen.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:119161:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119161:12"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIAN COMMONWEALTH: OR, <hi>The Civil Polity of the Riſing Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Commandment of the Lord, that a people ſhould enter into Covenant with the Lord to become his people, even in their Civil Society, as well as in their Church-Society <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 29. 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>You ſtand this day all of you, before the Lord your God; your Captains of your Tribes, your Elders and your Officers, with all the men of Iſrael<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> (11.) <hi>Your little ones, your wives, and the ſtranger that is in thy Camp,</hi> &amp;c. (12.) <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Lord thy God, and into his oath which he maketh with thee this day,</hi> (13.) <hi>That he may eſtabliſh thee to day for a people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf, and that he may be to thee a God, as he hath ſaid unto thee, and as he hath ſworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Iſaac and to Jacob.</hi>
                  </note> Whereby they ſubmit themſelves to be ruled by the Lord in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119161:13"/>
all things, receiving from him, both the platform of their Government, and all their Laws; which when they do, then Chriſt reigneth over them in all things, they being ruled by his Will, and by the Word of his Mouth <hi>(b).</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">(a) Iſai. 33. 22. <hi>The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Law-giver, the Lord is our King, he ſhall ſave us.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſubſtance of which Covenant, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of themſelves unto the Lord, to be ruled by him in all things, is this. That they do humbly confeſs their corruption by nature, and loſt condition; that they acknowledge the free grace <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 26. 1. <hi>ad</hi> 12. <hi>I profeſs this day unto the Lord thy God, that I am come into the Countrey, which the Lord thy God ſware unto thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to give us,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 5. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſpeak, and ſay before the Lord thy God, A Syrian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to periſh was my father, and he wont down into Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 7. <hi>And when we cried unto the Lord, he heard us,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 8. <hi>And the Lord brought us forth out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt with a mighty hand,</hi> &amp;c.</note> of God, in their redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by Chriſt, and in the promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel unto them, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king application thereof effectually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſouls: and therefore the Lord hath ſhewed his everlaſting Love unto them, and cauſed them inwardly by faith, to give up themſelves unto him, to be for ever his, to love, ſerve, and obey him, in all his Word and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: ſo now they do outwardly, &amp; ſolemnly with the reſt of Gods people joyn together ſo to do in their Civil Polity, receiving from the Lord, both the platform of their civil Government, as it is ſet down (in the eſſentials of it) in the holy Scriptures; and alſo all their Laws, which they reſolve through his grace, to fetch out of the Word of God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119161:13"/>
making that their only <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting no Law, Statute or Judgement valid, farther then it appeareth to ariſe and flow from the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Such as with a lively faith enter into or walk in this Covenant, do perform every Act (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are free from temptation) of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil converſation among men <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 31. <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi>
                  </note> by faith in obedience unto God. Inſtructing, that all ſhould do ſo, who take this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and if they do not, they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of breach of Covenant, before God. A willing ſubjection of a mans ſelf to Chriſt in this Covenant, is ſome hopeful ſign of ſome degree of faith in Chriſt, and love to God; and as a good preparative for a more neer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Chriſt in Church-fellowſhip, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: he that is willing to ſerve Chriſt by the Polity of the ſecond Table civilly, is in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of preparation to ſerve him, by the Polity of the firſt Table Eccleſiaſtically.</p>
               <p>The Child is implicitely comprehended in the Fathers Covenant <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 29. 14, 15. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with you onely do I make this Covenant this day, but with him that ſtandeth here this day before the Lord our God, and with him that is not here with us this day.</hi>
                  </note>, the Wife is explicitely comprehended in her Husbands, inſomuch that in her Widowhood ſhe and her Family are one, under the order of the Government of God.</p>
               <p>The particular form of Government, which is approved of God <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18. 23. <hi>If thou ſhalt do this thing, and God command thee ſo.</hi>
                  </note>, inſtituted by <hi>Moſes</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 18. 24. <hi>Moſes hearkened, and did all.</hi>
                  </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119161:14"/>
the ſons of Iſrael, (and profitable to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by any Nation or People, who reverence the command of God, and tremble at his Word) is this; that they chuſe <note n="d" place="margin">18. 21. <hi>Thou ſhalt provide able men.</hi> With Deut. 1. 13. <hi>Take ye wiſe men, and I will make them Rulers.</hi>
                  </note> unto themſelves Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of thouſands <note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 18. 25. Deut. 1. 15.</note>, of hundreds, of fifties and of tens, who ſhall govern according to the pure, holy, righteous, perfect and good Law of God <note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 1. 17. <hi>Fear not the face of man, for the judgement is Gods.</hi> 2 Chro. 19. 6. <hi>And ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what ye do: for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgement:</hi> Ezek. 44. 24. <hi>They ſhall judge it according to my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </note>, written in the Scriptures of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
               <p>The forming of which Platforme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deduced from the Scriptures, is: as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119161:14"/>
               <head>CHAP II.</head>
               <p>THe ſeveral degrees of tens, fifties, hundreds, and thouſands; may fitly be called orders of men, governed by God, the God of order <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 9. 7. <hi>Of the increaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no end, upon the throne of David, and upon his Kingdom, to order it.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Which orders of men are
<list>
                     <item>1. Thoſe of the ſingle Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</item>
                     <item>2. Thoſe of the Superior ariſing upon the firſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt for the ſingle Platform, which is Gods Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, according to which the Superior is delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or meaſured out. God hath commanded that ten men ſhould chuſe unto them a Ruler of ten.</p>
               <p>Hence, if they be not ten, they cannot chuſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a Ruler of ten. Hence alſo the Ruler maketh the eleventh man; or rather, is the head <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18. 25. <hi>Make them heads ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he  people, Rulers of tens,</hi> &amp;c.</note> of the order of ten.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo one Ruler of ten, may Rule over nineteen men; but if they become twenty, then by Gods inſtitution, they muſt chuſe another Ruler of ten; for God hath ſaid, <hi>Chuſe you Rulers of tens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Servants, or Sons living with their Parents, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119161:15"/>
in the condition of Servants <note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 4. 1. <hi>Tho heir ſo long as he is a child, differeth nothing from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
                  </note>, they may not explicitely, politically, perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, chuſe publick Rulers; while they live under the Authority of Family-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they are not perſonally capable of intereſt in publick Political Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: it is enough to attain Gods ends, that they be virtually comprehended in their Fathera Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>But if they Marry, or live in the ſtate of allowed publick Free-men, then are they capable of, &amp; are bound perſonally to act, in the choice of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blickRulers. The Rulers of the Father are virtually Rulers of the Child: but when the child putteth forth an act of choice, he hath liberty to chuſe, in due order, another Ruler of ten, unto whom he doth perſonally ſubmit himſelf: for all men are commanded to chuſe unto themſelves Rulers.</p>
               <p>By that one act of chuſing his Ruler of ten, and ſubjecting himſelf unto him, he doth chuſe, and ſubject himſelf unto all the Superior orders, under whom his Ruler of ten is ruled.</p>
               <p>No man may lawfully, or without ſin, live out of the order of Gods Government: and ſhould any man refuſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſubject himſelf unto the ſame, he cannot juſtly challenge any privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, benefit, or protection thereby, though his virtual intereſt (in ſuch as have it) hath hold upon him, until his actual choice doth more expreſly engage him; and Love will improve every thing for the good of thoſe, who know not what is good for themſelves. He is beneath the condition of a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119161:15"/>
ſtranger, who ſhall Apoſtatize from the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord; yea, beneath the condition of Barbarians, who are not yet come in, either by themſelves, or their Progenitors.</p>
               <p>As the Ruler of ten may rule over more then ten, even any number under twenty: ſo it is with the other orders, One Ruler of fifty, may rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver nine orders of ten; but if they become ten, then they muſt chuſe another Ruler of fifty: for the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>Chuſe you Rulers of fifties;</hi> that is, every five orders of ten ſhall chuſe a Ruler of fifty.</p>
               <p>Again, one Ruler of an hundred, may rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver three orders of fifties; but if they become four orders of fifties, then two of them muſt chuſe another Ruler: for God hath ſaid, <hi>Chuſe Rulers of hundreds;</hi> that is, of ten orders of tens.</p>
               <p>Again, one Ruler of a thouſand, may rule over nineteen orders of an hundred; but if they become twenty orders, then they muſt by Gods inſtitution chuſe another Ruler of a thouſand: for the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>Chuſe you Rulers of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence one Ruler of a thouſand may, in caſe all the orders under him be at the fulleſt, rule over 8436. men; which ordinarily, amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to 33687 ſouls: which doth thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>One Ruler of ten may rule over nineteen men.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119161:16"/>
One Ruler of fifty may rule over nine orders of ten; and nine times nineteen, maketh one hundred ſeventy one.</item>
                  <item>One Ruler of an hundred, may rule over three orders of fifty; and thrice 171, maketh 413.</item>
                  <item>One Ruler of a thouſand, may rule over nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen orders of an hundred; and nineteen times 413, maketh 7847.</item>
                  <item>Add therefore to the people, their Rulers, thus:</item>
                  <item>One Ruler of 50. with his nine Rulers of ten, make ten Rulers.</item>
                  <item>One Ruler of an 100. may rule over three or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of 50. which maketh 30. Rulers.</item>
                  <item>One Ruler of a thouſand, may have under him nineteen Rulers of an hundred. So that 19. times 30. and 19. added to them,</item>
                  <item>makes 589 Rulers</item>
                  <item>Add to them 7847 People</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Summa totalis</hi> is 8436</item>
               </list>
               <p>And generally among mankind, for one head of a Family, there be at leaſt three more ſouls of women and children: ſo that four times 8436. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth to 33687. ſoules. But it will be rare for all orders to be full at once.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119161:16"/>
Again, theſe orders of men, may be multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus: when ſuch as are Supernumerary in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral orders, agree together to make another or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For example, if two Rulers of ten, have each of them fifteen men under them, then five men of one order, and five of the other order, may agree together to make another, a new order: and ſo in all other orders it may be.</p>
               <p>But if they do this, if they make a new order becauſe they deſire it, and not becauſe the Word of the Lord commandeth it; when they multiply orders by choice, and not by neceſſity of inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: then their next Superiors ſhall guide and direct them in peace and mutual love: for <hi>Moſes</hi> guided the people in all their Elections <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 18. 21, 25. <hi>Thou ſhalt provide able men.</hi> 25. <hi>Moſes choſe able men.</hi> Deut. 1. 15. <hi>So I took the chief of your Tribes.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>If they cannot agree, then they may appeal to their next Superiours, and ſo unto the higheſt <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 1. 17. <hi>The caſe that is too hard for you, bring it unto me.</hi>
                  </note> Council, if need be: For the Council is (in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſpenſation) in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtead; and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are the Mouth of God, at which they muſt enquire, and by the guidance thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of all Caſes, ſo far as the Lord giveth light; and until the mind of God be known, the Caſe muſt ſtay, whatever it be <note n="c" place="margin">Num. 15. 34. <hi>And they put him in ward, becauſe it was not declared what ſhould be done unto him.</hi> Numb. 9. 8. <hi>Stand ſtill, and I will hear what the Lord will command concerning you.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119161:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe Lord hath given this Commandment in the ordering of his Government, that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be executed ſpeedily <note n="a" place="margin">Ezra 7. 26. <hi>Let judgment be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily upon them.</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 11. <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the ſons of men, is fully ſet in them to do evil.</hi>
                  </note>; and alſo that it ſhould be managed with the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the eaſe, both of the Governours, and People <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18. 17, 18, 22, 23. <hi>This thing is not good; thou wilt ſurely wear away, both thou and this people that is with thee:</hi> ver. 22. <hi>So ſhall it be eaſier:</hi> ver. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt be able to endure, and all the people ſhall go to their place in peace,</hi> viz. <hi>having judgement among themſelves in their own Quarters, and places of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, and not be troubled to come to the chief Court, with every cauſe.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>But particular times, means and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, the Lord hath not particularly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 18. 22. <hi>Let them judge the people at all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
                  </note>. Hence it is left unto the wiſdom of the Rulers, to order time, means and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, for the beſt, and moſt effectual attainment of the forementioned ſpeedy and eaſie determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and execution of Judgement, in all Caſes whatſoever, and in all places, Cities, or Towns where the people dwell <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 18. 23. <hi>All the people ſhall go to their own place in peace.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Hence again, it well accordeth with Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119161:17"/>
that every order do co-habit together <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 1. 15. <hi>I took the chief of your Tribes, and made them heads over you.</hi>
                  </note> as neer as may be; becauſe that doth tend to facilitate both the watch, and work of the Lords Government.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo limits of place <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 21. 2, 3. <hi>Thy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Judges ſhall meaſure unto the Cities about, and the City which is next unto the ſlain man.</hi> Deut. 16. 18. <hi>Judges ſhalt thou make in all thy gates throughout thy Tribes.</hi>
                  </note> (in a general ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation with allowance to ſome particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, as prudence and piety may require) may be uſeful to attain this end.</p>
               <p>Hence again, if any ſhall remove his habitation to a more remote place; meet it is that he do change his Rulers, by chuſing a Ruler of ten in the place whither he goeth to dwell: and hence it is meet that ſuch removings and changes be made by a due approbation of the Rulers whence he goeth, and with the acceptance of thoſe to whom he removeth, leſt by ſuch unſtable changes, as ſome may affect, they may ſlip out from under the Government of the Lord, at leaſt from under the watch and uſe thereof, though from the right thereof they cannot, becauſe it is a general com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to honour thy Father and thy Mother; and leſt by the confluence of unruly perſons to a place more remiſly governed, the Government of the Lord ſhould be undermined, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized.</p>
               <p>Becauſe ſin will grow apace, like ill weeds, if it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119161:18"/>
be not always watched, and often weeded out; and fire of ſtrife will ſoon flame out, if it be not ſpeedily ſuppreſſed and quenched: and it edifieth many ways, that juſtice ſhould be ſpeedily done; eſpecially it promoteth peace and piety.</p>
               <p>Hence it is meet, that Rulers of ten appoint one day in a week, ſolemnly to hear and determine Cauſes, and guide the common Affairs of his ten, for the more orderly, eaſie, and ſpeedy proceeding of juſtice and peace, which are facilitated and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited, by a ſtated and appointed time <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 18. 26. <hi>They judged the people at all ſeaſons:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>doth frequently in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſignifie a ſtated time.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Again, it is meet that the Ruler of fifty keep the Court of ſix, conſiſting of five Rulers of ten, and himſelf the Ruler of them, once in a moneth, for the more ſolemn proceeding of Juſtice, &amp; Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, if need be: becauſe the higher Caſes aſcend, the more ſolemnity is in them <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18. 22. <hi>Every great matter they ſhall bring unto thee.</hi>
                  </note>; and need the more time and deliberation.</p>
               <p>I call theſe a Court, becauſe they are an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Judges, among whom God promiſeth to ſtand <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 82. 1.</note>. Six is the loweſt number of this Court; but they may be more, according as the orders of ten be more under a Ruler of fifty; but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exceed ten; becauſe a Ruler of fifty cannot by Gods inſtitution, have more then nine orders of ten under him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119161:18"/>
Again, it is meet that the Ruler of an hundred keep the Court of three, conſiſting of two Rulers of fifty, and himſelf the Ruler of them, four times in the year, upon the former grounds.</p>
               <p>Three is the loweſt number of this Court, and it cannot exceed four; becauſe by Gods inſtitution, he cannot have more then three orders of fifty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him.</p>
               <p>Again, it is meet that the Ruler of a thouſand keep the Court of eleven, conſiſting of ten Rulers of an hundred, and himſelf the Ruler of them, twice in a year: and here judgement runneth with greateſt Solemnity and Majeſty; I ſay, Greateſt in the ſingle platform.</p>
               <p>Eleven is the loweſt number of this Court; but there may be more, according as the orders of an hundred under him be multiplied; but they cannot exceed twenty, becauſe he cannot have above nineteen orders of an hundred under him.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary that every Court have ſuch Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 16. 18. <hi>Judges and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers ſhalt thou make,</hi> Vide Ainſworth in Loc.</note> to attend, as are neceſſary to accompliſh and execute thoſe ends for which the Lord hath inſtituted thoſe Courts: becauſe the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the end, doth command all means requiſite for the attainment of that end, being ſuch as accords with Juſtice and Prudence.</p>
               <p>It is alſo neceſſary to have perſons <note n="a" place="margin">Lev. 24. 12. Num. 15 34. <hi>They put him in ward.</hi>
                  </note>, and all other Inſtruments, for the inflicting of all kindes of Puniſhments, which the Law of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119161:19"/>
But touching the ſeveral Puniſhments of Coſt, Shame, or Smart; and touching the ſeveral ways of putting to Death, by Stoning, Burning, Strangling, or by the Sword; as alſo touching Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, I am here ſilent. They more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appearing in the handling of ſuch Laws which do inflict ſeveral puniſhments, according to the demerit of the ſin, or uſe of terrour unto others, proportioning them to the Standard in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:119161:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>UPon the forenamed grounds of ſpeedy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for the ſtabliſhing of firme peace, all Cauſes betwixt man and man, pertaining to the Congnizance of the Ruler of ten, muſt be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Suit or Tryal, within the ſpace of one moneth <note n="b" place="margin">Lev. 19. 17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi>
                  </note>. Caſes belonging to the Court of ſix, muſt be put upon Suit or Tryal within the ſpace of three moneths. Cauſes belonging to the Court of three, muſt be put upon Suit or Tryal, within the ſpace of nine moneths. Cauſes belonging to the Court of eleven, muſt be put upon Suit or Tryal, in the ſpace of one year and half; or elſe to be fruſtrate, and loſe the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of receiving judgement by man; unleſs it appear that the providence of God did hinder, or that the Defendant or Delinquent party did diſappoint it: in thoſe caſes it may be admitted to Tryal, and receive Judgement, though it be of a longer ſtanding.</p>
               <p>But Criminal Offences are to be judged, at the time when, and in the place where they be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and that with the moſt ſpeed that may be.</p>
               <p>Such Caſes as are difficult, weighty, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſuch attendance, and cannot attain an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iſſue in the Court where they firſtly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, may aſcend from Court to Court, either by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119161:20"/>
Appeal, or by Tranſmiſſion to the Court of eleven. And whatſoever Cauſe of weight cannot receive iſſue there, may yet aſcend either by Appeal or Tranſmiſſion to the higheſt Council <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 18. 22. <hi>Great matters they ſhall bring to thee.</hi> 26. <hi>Hard matters they brought to Moſes.</hi> Deut. 17. 8, 9. <hi>If there ariſe a matter too hard for thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thou ſhalt come to the Priests, Levites and Judges that ſhall be in thoſe days.</hi>
                  </note>, where by Gods appointment it muſt receive final determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>And thou ſhalt do according to the ſentence,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 17. 10.</note>.</p>
               <p>In leſſer Commonwealths, where there be no Rulers or Courts of the Superiour order, Caſes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to the higheſt Council from the Court of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: but where there be Rulers and Courts of the Superiour order, there the Cauſe muſt aſcend from the Court of eleven in the ſingle Platform, to the Court of one Myriade, or the loweſt Court in the Superiour order; and ſo proceed until it come to the Supreme Council.</p>
               <p>Every Appeal in this Platform of Government which the Lord hath inſtituted, doth aſcend to an higher Court, and to other Judges. There is one of the Judges from whom he appealeth, a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Court to which he doth Appeal, truly to inform the Court of the Reaſons of their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and but one, leſt they ſhould ſway over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, and the Appealant want the priviledge of new and unprejudiced Judges.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall trouble the free paſſage of Juſtice in the ending of Cauſes, through a perverſe will, or baſe ends, or captious and quarrelſome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119161:20"/>
wit, beſides the charges of ſuch agitations, he is worthy of ſome other medicine, as may moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually do him good, and warn others.</p>
               <p>In all Courts, he that hath power to call the Court, hath a double Vote: as for example, in the Court of Three, if the Ruler of an hundred dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the two Rulers of fifty, the Court is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually divided: if there be three Rulers of fifty, and one of them concur with the Ruler of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, their ſentence ſtandeth.</p>
               <p>When the Court is equally divided, it is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Caſe, and muſt aſcend to the Court next a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them by Tranſmiſſion; or if the leſſer part of the Court oppoſe the ſentence of the Court, as judging it ſinful, then it muſt aſcend by Tranſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>If a Judge of any Court ſhall oppoſe the reſt in point of ſin, without weighty and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grounds, in the judgement of the Court whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it aſcends or is tranſmitted; his firſt offence ſhall be corrected with the charge of ſuch tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and admonition from the higher Court: after, offences in like kind are to be conſidered and judged, by proportion to the proceſs of Chriſt in the Church, even unto rejection from his Place and Office.</p>
               <p>The higheſt <hi>Council</hi> is to conſiſt of a convenient number of the moſt holy and able men <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 11. 16. <hi>Whom thou knoweſt, to be Elders of the people.</hi> With Exod. 18. 21. <hi>Able men, ſuch as fear God; men of truth, hating covetouſneſs.</hi>
                  </note> orderly choſen for that purpoſe, by all the orders of <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 1. 13. <hi>Take ye wiſe men.</hi>
                  </note> men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119161:21"/>
under their juriſdiction, every man in order ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an equal voice therein, from among all the Elders of the people: both in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and in the Churches <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 17. 9. <hi>And thou ſhalt come to the Prieſts, Levites, and Judges that ſhall be in thoſe days, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and they ſhall ſhew thee,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Chro. 19. 8. <hi>Moreover, in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem did Jehoſaphat ſet of the Levites, and of the Prieſts, and of the chief of the fathers in Iſrael, for the judgement of the Lord, and for controverſie.</hi> Deut. 21. 2. <hi>Then thy Elders and Judges ſhall come forth, and ſhall meaſure,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 5. <hi>And the Prieſts the ſons of Levi ſhall come neer, and by their word ſhall every ſtroke and every controverſie be tryed.</hi> Deut. 19. 17. <hi>Both the men between whom the controverſie is, ſhall ſtand before the Lord, before the Prieſts and Judges.</hi> Ezek. 44. 24. <hi>And in controverſie they ſhall stand in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they ſhall judge it according to my judgement.</hi>
                  </note>, the biggeſt number being civil Elders <note n="d" place="margin">Numb. 11. 16. <hi>Gather to me ſeventy men of the Elders of Iſrael.</hi> Vide Ainſw. in Loc. <hi>Hence the Hebrews gather, that they were choſe out of all the Tribes, and therefore there was not leſs then five of a Tribe, and ſo many of Levi, who before the institution of the Sanhedrim, were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God inſtead of the firſt born, to be Prieſts unto God: for they were taken to be Prieſts at Sinai,</hi> Numb. 3. 14. <hi>And this inſtitution was at Kibroth-hattaavah,</hi> Numb. 11. 34. with Numb. 31. 15, 16, 17.</note>.</p>
               <p>The Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> that ſeventy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhould ſtand with him before the Lord; hence there were ſeventy one of the Council, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was the chief, and ordained the reſt.</p>
               <p>According to which patern, the people are to chuſe their chief Ruler firſt; who being inſtalled by ſome, inſtead of the whole people, muſt inſtal the reſt, and is chief Ruler of the Supreme Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, who muſt call and manage their Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119161:21"/>
As the overburdenſomneſs of the work of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by one man, was the ground of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the forenamed orders of Government: ſo the overburdenſomneſs of the work for one man to hear all hard Caſes, and Appeals, together with other Cares to provide for the welfare of the people, was the ground of the inſtitution of the Supreme Council <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 1. 9. <hi>I ſpake to you, and ſaid, I am not able to bear you alone.</hi> Numb. 11. 11. ad 16. ver. 11. <hi>And Moſes ſaid unto the Lord, Wherefore haſt thou afflicted thy ſervant, and wherefore have I not found favour in thy ſight, that thou layest the burden of all this people upon me?</hi> ver. 14. <hi>I am not able to bear all the people alone, becauſe it is too heavy for me.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>The conveniency of the number of this high Council, is thus to be meaſured, and judged by Gods Standard. Iſrael had at leaſt three Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people, (though not one Million of men in order, or not much more: for the Souldiers were but ſix hundred thouſand) now their Supreme Council conſiſted of ſeventy one; therefore that is the higheſt number that will be needed among men ordinarily; yea, though a people ſhould be much bigger, I ſee not but that number may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: But that number is not limitted; becauſe God denyeth not this Government to fifty who are the leaſt Court, and a leſſer number of men then the higheſt Council in Iſrael had, by Gods appointment; and if it be not limitted on the one ſide, ſo nor on the other.</p>
               <p>Again, the loweſt number of the Supreme Council that may be, is five; becauſe that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119161:22"/>
muſt conſiſt both of Magiſtrates, and Elders of Churches; Elders of both ſorts; one of a ſort ſufficeth not, and the bigger part muſt be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</p>
               <p>This Council muſt alwaies be in being, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally or virtually, to give anſwer to all Caſes propounded, touching the Law of God, and the application thereof, to any particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Cauſe, and to take care for the general Protection, Proviſion, and Government of the whole, in truth, holineſs, and peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119161:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THe duties of all the Rulers of the civil part of the Kingdom of Chriſt, are as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Office and Duty of all the Rulers, is to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the people in the orderly and ſeaſonable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all the Commandments of God, in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons liable to Political obſervation, whether of piety and love to God, or of juſtice, and love to man with peace.</p>
               <p>Hence they are keepers of both Tables, and are ſo to look that all the Commandments of God be obſerved, as to compel men to their undoubted duty, and puniſh them for their undoubted ſins, errours and tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>A Caſe, a Duty, a Sin, is ſaid then to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, when either it is expreſly, or by general approved conſequence, commanded or forbidden in the Scriptures; or when it hath paſſed the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of Gods Polity, and received its final deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination according to the Scriptures; unto which not to ſubmit, is capital preſumption.</p>
               <p>Hence again, Rulers are eminently concerned to maintain the purity of Religion, with all care and power; holineſs, truth, and peace being much concerned herein.</p>
               <p>Hence again, all Rulers muſt be skilful in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119161:23"/>
Scriptures; they muſt read and meditate in the ſame all the daies of their life, that thereby they may be enabled to do their Office faithfully, and religiouſly ſo long as they live.</p>
               <p>Hence again, they are to give counſel and command for the well ordering of all the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs of their people; both in Education of Youth, whether in Schools or other Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations; in walking in their Callings, in their Neighbourhood, commerce and converſe with men, in ſubjecting themſelves to Government, with Religion, Juſtice and Peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119161:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>THe Office of the Ruler of ten, is to ſee all his people walk as becometh Gods people in their ſeveral places, furthering the ſame upon all occaſions. And at appointed times to ſit alone, to hear and determine Cauſes of Juſtice, and of evil converſation; to declare Gods ſentence and counſel in every Caſe, and ſee it executed.</p>
               <p>Provided it be with the conſent and ſubmiſſion of the party or parties concerned.</p>
               <p>All difficult Caſes, and Appeals, he ſhall binde over to the Court of ſix; and Capitals in life, limb or baniſhment, to the Court of eleven.</p>
               <p>Theſe Rulers are next the people; hence they ſee them <note n="*" place="margin">Each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> moſt: and therefore they need be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly wiſe, patient, loving, faithful, and zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy men. So great is his work and charge, that it had need extend but to a ſmall compaſs. If he well perform his Office, it doth prevent much trouble to Superiour Courts.</p>
               <p>The Office of the Ruler of fifty, is to ſee that all the Rulers often under him, be faithful in their Office and Duty; and to help on their work, in all Caſes, and toward all perſons, as he hath occaſion.</p>
               <p>As alſo to call and keep the Court of ſix in their ſeaſons; where all Caſes, pertaining to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good of all his order, and particular Caſes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119161:24"/>
betwixt parties of the ſeveral of the orders of ten under him, are nextly to be tryed and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, together with Appeals from any of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of ten under him: and difficult Caſes tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from them to this Court.</p>
               <p>This Court hath power to end ſtrifes, judge Cauſes, declare and pronounce the ſentence of Gods Word, in mulcts, and puniſhments, and ſee them executed. Difficult Caſes they ſhall tranſmit; and alſo Appeals they ſhall bind over, unto the Court of three. But capitals in life, limb or baniſhment, to the Court of eleven.</p>
               <p>The Office of the Ruler of an hundred, is to ſee that the Rulers of fifty under him, do perform their Office and Duty faithfully; to help them what lieth in him, in any of their works towards their Rulers of ten, or any particular perſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. Alſo all Cauſes which concern the Publick good of all Orders under him, are in his charge. And alſo to call and keep the Court of three, where Cauſes betwixt parties of his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral orders of fifty, are properly to be tryed and determined; with Appeals from the Court of ſix, and ſuch difficult Caſes as that Court ſhall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them.</p>
               <p>This Court hath power to end all ſtrifes, judge and determine Cauſes, declare and pronounce the ſentence of Gods Word, in mulcts and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and ſee them executed. Alſo to take care of the Publick good of all their Orders. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, difficult Caſes, and capitals in life and limb, and baniſhment, they ſhall bind over and tranſmit to the Court of eleven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119161:24"/>
The Office of the Ruler of a thouſand, is to ſee that all the Rulers of hundreds under him, do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Office and duty faithfully; to help them what lieth in him in any part of their charge toward their Rulers of fifties, or Rulers of ten, or any perſon under him; alſo all Caſes which concern the Publick good of all the orders under him, are in his care and charge. As alſo to call and keep the Court of eleven, where all Cauſes betwixt perſons in ſeveral of his Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, are properly belonging; with Appeals from the Court of three, and difficult Caſes tranſmitted to them. Alſo all Caſes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Publick good of all the Orders under them.</p>
               <p>Alſo all capital Caſes of life, limb or baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, belong this Court: becauſe it is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt ſolemn Judicatory in the ſingle Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and fulleſt of Majeſty. The higheſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is fitly pronounced, in a more ſolemn Judicatory, then is the Court of ſix, or three; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the ſmalneſs or paucity of the people have no higher.</p>
               <p>Alſo Caſes betwixt parties of ſeveral thouſands belong to this Court: at the choice of the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff in which Court of eleven, either that which himſelf doth belong to, or that which his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary is under. But this conſideration doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to leſſer Commonwealths, where they have no Governour of the Superiour order, and yet more then one Ruler of a thouſand.</p>
               <p>This Court hath power to hear and judge all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119161:25"/>
Cauſes brought before them; declare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence of Scripture, in all mulcts and puniſhments, even death it ſelf, and ſee them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted.</p>
               <p>Alſo to pronounce, and ſee executed, all ſuch ſentences as the Supreme Council doth deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and remit unto them. Namely, thus it is in leſſer Commonwealths, where there be no Courts of the Superiour order, difficult Caſes they muſt tranſmit to the higheſt Council, and bind over Appeals unto them, where there be no Courts of the Superiour order, betwixt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Council and them.</p>
               <p>The Office of the Supreme Council, is to ſee that all the Rulers of thouſands, yea, all Rulers and Officers, of all orders and degrees, do their Office and Duty faithfully; and to receive dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Caſes and Appeals, from the Court of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven; to ſearch the Scriptures with all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to find out the pure mind of God, impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and ſincerely to apply the Cauſe propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereunto; to declare the will of God in the Caſe, and ſo return it to the Court of eleven, whereto it appertaineth, there to receive judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accordingly. And whoſoever will do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, and not hearken unto that ſentence, ſhall be put to death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 11, 12.</p>
               <p>In the ſingle Platform, the Court of eleven is next to the Supreme Council, for tranſmiſſion and remiſſion of Cauſes; but where there be Courts of the Superiour order, it is not ſo.</p>
               <p>Alſo they are to declare the Counſel and Will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119161:25"/>
of God, touching War and Peace, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly tranſmit the work to ſuch of the Rulers as they judge moſt meet to accompliſh the ſame.</p>
               <p>Alſo to take care for, and provide means for Publick welfare and ſubſiſtence, by Trading, both Foraign and Domeſtick, Fiſhing, Tillage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with all other neceſſary and uſeful Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially they are to take care for peace and truth in Religion, in all the Churches, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the people; and the propagation alſo thereof. As alſo the furtherance of all good lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all the Liberal Arts and Sciences.</p>
               <p>The Supreme Council, and all Courts, yea, and all Rulers, have power to bind Offenders, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned, to appear, or proſecute in due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſeaſon; puniſh for offences in that kind; and if need be, commit to priſon for ſecurity.</p>
               <p>If Rulers offend either morally or politically, by rigor, partiality or remiſneſs, his or their next Superiours have power to correct ſuch evils, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God; and as need may be, the Caſe may orderly aſcend, from Court to Court, even to the higheſt Council. Hereſie, Blaſphemy, and other groſs (eſpecially if capital) ſins, are juſt cauſe, in due order, of depoſition from his Office, by the Supreme Council; the Cauſe coming to them either by orderly aſcent, or taken in immediately, as a notorious ſcandal, which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for ſpeedy remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119161:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>SO much for the ſingle Platform of Chriſt his Government: now followeth the Superiour, ariſing out of the firſt.</p>
               <p>When the Lord ſhall bow the hearts of great Nations, to embrace this form of Government, there being populous Cities, Provinces, and Countries, where the Rulers of thouſands will be greatly multiplied, and Cauſes frequently fall out, betwixt parties of ſeveral thouſands; yea, and betwixt the Rulers of thouſands ſometimes, being ſo numerous, inſomuch that the Supreme Council will be overburdened, even as <hi>Moſes</hi> was.</p>
               <p>Hence there will be a neceſſity of erecting the Superiour platform of the Lords Government: which by proportion unto the ſingle Platforme (which is more fully expreſt in Scripture) doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from it, and is builded upon it.</p>
               <p>Namely, that every ten orders of thouſands, ſhould chuſe a Ruler of ten thouſand, or a Myri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade; and five orders of Myriades, a Ruler of fifty thouſand, or five Myriades; and two orders of five Myriades ſhould chuſe a Ruler of an hundred thouſand, or ten Myriades: and ten orders of an heundred thouſands, or ten Myriades, ſhould chuſe a Ruler of a thouſand thouſand, or an hundred Myriades, or a Million.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119161:26"/>
I am led to believe, that this Superiour order of Rulers, is a Divine inſtitution, not only by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of proportion to the ſingle Platform; but expreſly, and that it was practiſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: namely, that ten Rulers of thouſands had a Ruler over them of ten thouſands, or of a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riade; and that the order of Myriades or ten thouſands, were as duly &amp; orderly obſerved, as the orders of thouſands were. For <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. 36. when they reſted from their marching, <hi>Moſes</hi> bleſſed them, and ſaid, <hi>Return O Lord, to the Myriades of the thouſands of Iſrael:</hi> therefore there were orders of Myriades, as well as of thouſands.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, it is expreſly ſaid, by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his ſong, Deut. 33. 2. <hi>The Lord came from Sinai</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where the order of Government was firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted) <hi>and he came with myriades of Saints.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore orders of Myriades were inſtituted and acted from the firſt foundation of this Government.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 17. he ſpeaketh of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Myriades among the Tribes, as familiarly obſervable, as the orders of thouſands. So that we may ſee this Superiour order and platform of Government, obſerved in Iſrael, and expreſſed in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The Ruler of a Myriade hath this eminency, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Ruler often in the ſingle Platform, that all his ten whom he immediately ruleth, are eminent Rulers.</p>
               <p>Hence they are an Aſſembly of Judges, and a Court, for number every way proportionable to the Court of eleven: but for eminency and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119161:27"/>
they are more properly called the Court of one Myriade.</p>
               <p>The Ruler of fifty thouſand or five Myriades holdeth a Court for number proportionable to the Court of ſix in the ſingle Platform: but for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and diſtinction, they are more properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Court of five Myriades.</p>
               <p>The Ruler of an hundred thouſand, or ten My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riades, holdeth a Court for number proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Court of three in the ſingle Platform: but for eminency and diſtinction, it is more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the Court of ten Myriades.</p>
               <p>The Ruler of a thouſand thouſand, or an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Myriades, holdeth a Court for number pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the Court of eleven; but for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and diſtinction, it is more properly called the Court of one hundred Myriades.</p>
               <p>The times or ſeaſons, Officers or other means for the moſt effectual ordering of theſe Courts, will be moſt fitly diſcerned, and agreed, by ſuch a people as may have uſe of them.</p>
               <p>The Cauſes which moſt properly belong to the Court of one Myriade, are ſuch as fall out betwixt parties of their ſeveral thouſands; as alſo difficult Caſes tranſmitted from the Court of eleven, and Appeals from them.</p>
               <p>Alſo all ſuch Caſes as concern the Publick good of all under them.</p>
               <p>All Courts of the Superiour order have power to judge all capital Caſes whatſoever.</p>
               <p>The Court of one Myriade hath alſo power to judge any Cauſe betwixt the Rulers of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119161:27"/>
of that Myriade, who are not to judge in the Court when their own Caſe is judged. Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Caſes they tranſmit, and Appeals they bind over to the Court of five Myriades, if there be ſuch a Court betwixt them and the Supreme Council: otherwiſe they tranſmit them to the Council.</p>
               <p>The Cauſes which properly belong to the Court of five Myriades, are ſuch as fall out betwixt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſeveral Myriades under them.</p>
               <p>I will aſcend no higher, in deſcribing the Courts of the Superiour order: party becauſe Gods Method is plain, and alſo it will be rarely of uſe in any Commonwealth; eſpecially conſidering that which I farther propound.</p>
               <p>Namely, ſeeing God himſelf was pleaſed to appoint a Prince, a chief Ruler, over every Tribe in Iſrael, who were diſtinguiſhed, by that civil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of kindreds:</p>
               <p>By proportion thereunto, in populous Nations, where there be other civil diſtinctions of ſocieties and cohabitations of men, <hi>viz.</hi> by Cities, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Countries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould not they chuſe a Prince, a chief Ruler of thoſe ſeveral Precincts of civil ſociety?</p>
               <p>Whoſe Office is chiefly to take care of the good Government, firſtly, of all the Superiour Rulers under him; as alſo of all the reſt, as he hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that the Lord may rule among them.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe to hold a Court, conſiſting either of the Rulers of Myriades, or of five Myriades, or of ten Myriades, or of an hundred Myriades,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119161:28"/>
according to the greatneſs of the people in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts.</p>
               <p>This Court to be called the Court of the Prince, or Lord, or chief Ruler of ſuch a Precinct; and to be next unto the Supreme Council: from which Court, onely difficult Caſes and Appeals have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the Supreme Council, and to which they remit the determinations of the Cauſe, to receive its judgement: Leſt the Supreme Council be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with buſineſs from ſo many Courts, and thereby the people with delays of hearing and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, occaſioned thereby.</p>
               <p>It ſeemeth to be right Orders, and according to Gods inſtitution, that theſe Princes of the ſeveral Tribes or Societies of men ſhould be members of the Supreme Council: The whole Dominion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtributed unto the Supreme Counſellours, or to ſo many of them as may be meet. For the Princes of the Tribes of Iſrael (it ſeemeth to me) were members of the Sanhedrim or Supreme Council; becauſe God commanded that they ſhould be choſen very carefully from among the Elders of the people. Hence they will chuſe the moſt choice of their Elders to ſend up with <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſtand before God. Now they could not chuſe better, fitter, and men more acceptable to God, out of all their Elders, then thoſe whom God himſelf had choſen by name, to be Princes of the Tribes.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is exceedingly harmonious, in the frame of this Government, that it ſhould be ſo: for though whoever of the other Elders, whether of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119161:28"/>
the ſingle or Superiour Order, be choſen to the Supreme Council, it may ſeem requiſite, they ſhould leave the lower ſtation, leſt when Appeals have paſſed in the circuit of Gods Government, and come to the higheſt Council, there ſhould be ſundry of them, through whoſe judgement the Cauſe had formerly paſſed, which may prove pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial both to their perſons, and to the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But when it hath laſtly paſſed through the Court of the Prince of the Tribe, meet it is that one of the laſt Court through which it paſſed, ſhould be preſent in the Supreme Council, to give true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, how they laſtly after all former Tryals did find the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But this is to be obſerved in the diſtribution of the whole Dominion to the ſeveral Supreme Counſellours, that no ſuch civil Dominion is to be put upon or accepted by ſuch Elders of Churches, as are Members of the high Council; as being ſuch whoſe only Office and Work is to ſearch the holy Scriptures, and give all attendance to declare the Divine Oracle of God in ſuch Caſes as are in hand, of what nature ſoever they be: yea, and if the Council ſee need, to call Ecceſiaſtical Councils, greater or leſſer, to ſearch out the mind of Chriſt; for his preſence and bleſſing is in every Ordinance; and all joyntly conſpire the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Kingdom, and the doing of his will.</p>
               <p>The Election of all Superiour Rulers, is to be after the ſame manner as in the ſingle form, <hi>viz.</hi> by all the people <note n="*" place="margin">Or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of men.</note>, over whom they are to rule.</p>
               <p>Some of the Princes of the Tribes of Iſrael, may
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119161:29"/>
ſeem to be Rulers of fifty thouſands, or of five Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Myriades: yet the Office of the Princes was not onely under that notion, but alſo as an head of a civil ſociety, a kindred, an eminent part, a diviſion of the Commonwealth: for ſome of the Tribes had but four Myriades, and ſome but three, and therefore could not in that way and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der have a Ruler of five Myriades. Therefore they muſt needs be inſtituted under another conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <hi>viz.</hi> as being the head or chief Ruler over an eminent part, or diviſion of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, being civilly divided into ſuch Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119161:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>SO much for the Platform of the Lords Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now it remains to conſider of the Laws by which theſe Rulers are to Govern the Lords people. The written Word of God is the perfect Syſteme or Frame of Laws, to guide all the Moral actions of man, either towards God or man: the Application whereof to every Caſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its circumſtances, muſt be by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and diſcretion of the Judges, guided by the light of the Scriptures, and a pure Conſcience.</p>
               <p>The judgement and determination of a Cauſe, is nothing elſe, but the particular application of the Cauſe, according to all its circumſtances, unto the Rule and Standard of Gods Word.</p>
               <p>The Records of which judgements, are equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to Humane Laws. Which ſo far as the Caſe with all its circumſtances conſidered is rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the Rule of the Word, is a deduct from Scripture, and bindeth the Conſciences, both of Judges alway ſo to judge in the like caſe, and the people ſo to walk.</p>
               <p>Which Records to order wiſely, and publiſh for common inſtruction and edification, is a work of great wiſdom, and tendeth much to Gods glory, the good of the people, and the facilitating and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediting juſtice, among them. All Strangers, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be accounted under the Government of thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders where they reſide, and where their buſineſs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; ſo as to have the benefit of the Government of the Lord, as our own people have.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
